Register of the Eugene Lyons Papers 1919-1981
Hoover Institution Archives
Eugene Lyons papers
1919-1981
85006
Hoover Institution Archives
17 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes, 10 envelopes, 2 albums, 6 phonotapes, 13 phonorecords (10 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, notes, pamphlets, other printed matter, photographs, and sound recordings, relating primarily to conditions in the Soviet Union under communism, the international communist movement, and the career of Herbert Hoover.
Lyons, Eugene, 1898-1985
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1985.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Contents note
Correspondence, writings, notes, pamphlets, other printed matter, photographs, and sound recordings, relating primarily to conditions in the Soviet Union under communism, the international communist movement, and the career of Herbert Hoover.
Biographical Note
1898, July 1 Born, Uzlian, Russia
1907 Arrived in the United States
1917-18 Student, College City of New York
1918 Private, U.S. Army
1918-19 Student, Columbia University
1919 Naturalized as United States citizen
1920 Employee, Erie Dispatch (Pennsylvania)
1922 Employee, Boston Telegram
1922-23 Editor, Soviet Russia Pictorial
1923-27 Assistant Director, Tass Agency
1927 Author, The Life and Death of Sacco and Vanzetti
1928-1934 United Press correspondent in the Soviet Union
1934 Author, Six Soviet Plays
1935 Author, Moscow Carousel
1935-39 Member, Ames and Norr Public Relations
1937 Author, Assignment in Utopia
1937 Editor, We Cover the World
1939-1944 Editor, The American Mercury
1940 Author, Stalin, Czar of all the Russias
1941 Author, The Red Decade
1944-45 Editor, Pageant
1946-1968 Editor, The Readers Digest
1948 Author, Our Unknown Ex-President, a Portrait of Herbert Hoover
1951-52 President, American Committee for the Liberation of the Peoples of Russia
1953 Author, Our Secret Allies: The Peoples of Russia
1959 Author, The Herbert Hoover Story
1964 Author, Herbert Hoover: a Biography
1966 Author, David Sarnoff: a Biography
1967 Author, Workers' Paradise Lost: 50 Years of Soviet Communism: a Balance Sheet
1985, January 10 Died, New York City
Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Communism.; Journalists.; Phonorecords.; Phonotapes.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--History.; Soviet Union.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Politics and government.
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1934-1981 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, legal documents, clippings and printed matter, relating to Eugene Lyons' career, financial matters, health, and family.
- CORRESPONDENCE FILE, 1938-1981 (Box 1-2)
  Letters, including attached reports, memoranda, printed material, notes and clippings. Arranged alphabetically.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1919-1976 (Box 2-12)
  Typescript and printed copies, with related notes and source materials, reviews, memoranda, press releases, clippings, correspondence, and miscellany. Arranged chronologically.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1935-1980 (Box 12-16)
  Correspondence, reports, memoranda, clippings, notes, articles, newsletters, and miscellany. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
- PAMPHLET FILE, 1929-1976 (Box 16-17)
  Pamphlets arranged alphabetically by author or issuing agency.
- OVERSIZE FILE, 1928-1967 (Box 18-19)
  Scrapbooks, clippings, album, relating to E. Lyons' career, the Soviet Union, and the Spanish Civil War in 1936.
- MEMORABILIA (Box 20)
  Two plaques and two other items from E. Lyons' career as author and journalist.
- PHONORECORDS
  13 phonorecords of speeches by E. Lyons and Daniel Lyons relating to conditions and events in the Soviet Union, 1917-1975. Included is a Radio Liberty program on Boris Pasternak.
- CASSETTE TAPE
  1 cassette tape of speech by Colonel James E. Norwood entitled "Victory Over Communism: What You Can Do to Make It Happen," March 18, 1971.
- PHONOTAPES, 1963-1938
  5 phonotapes of E. Lyons' speeches.
- PHOTOGRAPHS
  641 prints / 10 envelopes / 2 albums
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1934-1981
  - Addresses, calling cards (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Awards, certificates (Folder 2)
  - Biographical notes (Folder 3)
  - Clippings (Folder 4-5)
  - Insurance on personal possessions, 1970 (Folder 6)
  - Lease on Moscow apartment, 1934 (Folder 7)
  - Lyons, Yetta, medical history, 1968-1973 (Folder 8)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1938-1981
  - General
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 9-12)
    - Russian refugees in Carinthia, Austria, 1949 (Folder 13)
    - Unidentified (Folder 14)
  - Adler, Julius, 1950 (Folder 15)
  - Allilueva, Svetlana, 1967, 1969 (Folder 16)
  - Alsop, Joseph, 1953 (Folder 17)
  - American Committee for Liberation, 1959 (Folder 18)
  - Antin, Anthony, 1976 (Folder 19)
  - Arlington House Publishers, 1976 (Folder 20)
  - Aronina, Ida, 1977 (Folder 21)
  - Ball, George W., 1972 (Folder 22)
  - Berger, Ira M., 1976 (Folder 23)
  - Bergman, B. A., 1967 (Folder 24)
  - Blagowidow, George, 1976 (Folder 25)
  - Brock, Irene, 1978 (Folder 26)
  - Brownell, William, 1976-77 (Folder 27)
  - Buckley, William F., 1968-69, 1976, 1978 (Folder 28)
  - Burnham, James, 1969 (Folder 29)
  - Callaway, Lew L. ( Newsweek), 1967 (Folder 30)
  - Canby, Vincent, 1971 (Folder 31)
  - Center for the Survival of Western Democracies, 1979 (Folder 32)
  - Chellson, Elizabeth, 1978 (Folder 33)
  - Colebrook, Joan, 1974 (Folder 34)
  - Conquest, Robert, 1968-69 (Folder 35)
  - Corletti, Lawrence A., 1975 (Folder 36)
  - Cowles, Gardner, 1967 (Folder 37)
  - Davis, Jerome, 1950 (Folder 38)
  - Deal Lake Motel, Asbury Park, New Jersey, 1976 (Folder 39)
  - Dodd, Thomas J., 1964 (Folder 40)
  - Dodds, Harold W., 1964 (Folder 41)
  - Dutch Treat Club, 1978 (Folder 42)
  - Eastman, Max, 1953, 1965 (Folder 43)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1964 (Folder 44)
  - Elez, Andrew, 1981 (Folder 45)
  - Ellender, Allen J., 1958-59 (Folder 46)
  - Estabrook, Howard, 1969 (Folder 47)
  - Forster, Mr., 1962 (Folder 48)
  - Geltman, Max, 1979 (Folder 49)
  - Glenny, Michael, 1969 (Folder 50)
  - Gotlieb, Howard B., 1965 (Folder 51)
  - Granfar, Moosa, 1959 (Folder 52)
  - Greenwood Press, 1977 (Folder 53)
  - Grunblatt, David, 1979 (Folder 54)
  - Hansen, Clifford P., 1967 (Folder 55)
  - Harriman, W. Averell, 1963 (Folder 56)
  - Hatfield, Mark, 1979 (Folder 57)
  - Henderson, Loy, 1974 (Folder 58)
  - Hillman, Rita K., 1975 (Folder 59)
  - Hook, Sidney, 1968 (Folder 60)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1959 (Folder 61)
  - Hoover, Herbert Jr., 1960, 1963 (Folder 62)
  - Human Events, 1959 (Folder 63)
  - Internal Revenue Service, 1979 (Folder 64)
  - Johnson, Allen, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Johnson, Lyndon B., 1962 (Folder 2)
  - Kaganski, Zakhary, 1934 (Folder 3)
  - Kastner, Alton, 1960 (Folder 4)
  - Kaufman, Bel, 1964, 1966 (Folder 5)
  - Kohler, Foy D., 1976 (Folder 6)
  - Labin, Suzanne, 1970 (Folder 7)
  - Lamont, Corliss, 1964 (Folder 8)
  - Lewis, Hobart, 1973 (Folder 9)
  - Lewis, Marx, 1967 (Folder 10)
  - Linville, Dr., 1938 (Folder 11)
  - Litante, Judith, 1979 (Folder 12)
  - Lodge, John Davis, 1967 (Folder 13)
  - Lofton, John D., 1964 (Folder 14)
  - Lovestone, Jay, 1967 (Folder 15)
  - Lyons, Dan, 1976, 1979 (Folder 16)
  - Lyons, Gretchen, n.d. (Folder 17)
  - Marin, Luis Munoz, 1960 (Folder 18)
  - Matthews, Ruth I., 1979 (Folder 19)
  - May, Ronald W., 1959 (Folder 20)
  - Methvin, Gene, 1967 (Folder 21)
  - Montgomery, Robert H., 1958 (Folder 22)
  - Munson, Lyle H., 1963 (Folder 23)
  - Muntzel, R. J., 1963 (Folder 24)
  - Navrozov, Lev, 1974 (Folder 25)
  - New York Times Magazine, 1959 (Folder 26)
  - Nixon, Richard M., 1961, 1963, 1968 (Folder 27)
  - Norwood, James E., 1968, 1975 (Folder 28)
  - Overseas Press Club of America, 1979 (Folder 29)
  - Possony, Stefan, 1975 (Folder 30)
  - Raynes, Julius, 1971 (Folder 31)
  - Reagan, Ronald, 1966 (Folder 32)
  - Reid, Helen, 1953 (Folder 33)
  - Robinson, Ione, 1976 (Folder 34)
  - Roche, John P., 1968 (Folder 35)
  - Russell, Mr., 1961 (Folder 36)
  - Samuel French, Inc., 1980 (Folder 37)
  - Sargent, Wyn, 1968 (Folder 38)
  - Sarnoff, David, 1952, 1965 (Folder 39)
  - Scott, John, 1976 (Folder 40)
  - Seversky Electronatom Corporation, 1975 (Folder 41)
  - Smith, Harrison, 1952 (Folder 42)
  - Sourwine, J. G., 1974 (Folder 43)
  - Spivak, Lawrence, 1977 (Folder 44)
  - Sulzberger, Mr., 1950 (Folder 45)
  - Sutton, Anthony, 1968 (Folder 46)
  - Thayer, Peter J., 1978 (Folder 47)
  - Thomas, Lowell, 1967 (Folder 48)
  - Truman, Harry S., 1964 (Folder 49)
  - Tyrmand, Mr., 1968 (Folder 50)
  - U.S. Information Agency, 1966-67 (Folder 51)
  - University of Oregon Library, 1966, 1980 (Folder 52)
  - Voice Publishing Company (Seoul, Korea), 1971 (Folder 53)
  - Wallace, De Witt, 1959, 1971, 1976 (Folder 54)
  - Welch, Robert, 1959 (Folder 55)
  - Whitehill, F. S., n.d. (Folder 56)
  - Wick, James L., 1964 (Folder 57)
  - Wiley, Charles, 1960 (Folder 58)
  - Wolfe, Bertram D., 1973 (Folder 59)
  - Yoken, Mel B., 1976 (Folder 60)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1923-1975
  - General
    - Undated articles, drafts, notes (Box 2, Folder 61-62)
    - Undated articles, drafts, notes (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
    - 1919-1945 (Folder 5)
    - 1946-1954 (Folder 6)
    - 1946-1955 (Folder 7)
    - 1956-58 (Folder 8)
    - 1956-1964 (Folder 9)
    - 1956-1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1959-1963 (Folder 2)
    - 1959-1974 (Folder 3)
    - 1966-1974 (Folder 4)
    - Correspondence relating to various articles and books, 1937-39 (Folder 5)
    - Research notes and clippings
      - Khrushchev, Nikita S., research notes (Folder 6)
      - Lenin, Vladimir I. Research notes, clippings.
        - General (Folder 7-8)
        - After, 1905 (Folder 9)
        - Armand, Inessa (Folder 10)
        - Character, personality (Folder 11)
        - Chernyshevsky and other influences (Box 5, Folder 1)
        - Childhood, youth (Folder 2)
        - Death and embalment (Folder 3)
        - German funding (Folder 4)
        - Last years (Folder 5)
        - Petersburg and Siberian exile (Folder 6)
        - Sealed train and arrival in Petrograd (Folder 7)
      - Soviet Union. Research notes, clippings.
        - Authors, poets, and the Kremlin (Folder 8-9)
        - Fiftieth anniversary, 1967 (Folder 10-11)
      - U.S. foreign relations, 1961. (Folder 12)
  - "The Apotheosis of Lenin: Stalin's Revenge," Typescript., n.d. (Folder 13)
  - "Chassidism," Typescript and handwritten draft. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "A Clinical Study in Political Hypocricy," Typescript., n.d. (Folder 2)
  - "Detente: A Dangerous Western Fantasy," Typescript., n.d. (Folder 3)
  - "Detente: The Great Hoax or the Appeasements That Failed," Typescript., n.d. (Folder 4)
  - "Education a la Carte," Typescript., n.d. (Folder 5)
  - "Epitaph for Anna Louise," Typescript., n.d. (Folder 6)
  - "The Ferments in Soviet Youth," Typewritten draft with annotations. (Folder 7)
  - "Former People," Typescript., n.d. (Folder 8)
  - "Hard to Take 'Naked Truth'," radio broadcast, "Opinioncasts," Broadcast Editorial Reports (NY), Printed copy., n.d. (Folder 9)
  - "Is Dulles Fit to Be Secretary of State," Typescript., n.d. (Folder 10)
  - "Law," Typescript., n.d. (Folder 11)
  - "The Man Who Quarreled With His Ghosts," Typescript., n.d. (Folder 12)
  - "Peace Symbol - A Kremlin Football," radio broadcast, "Opinioncasts," Broadcast Editorial Reports (NY), Printed copy., n.d. (Folder 13)
  - "The Poet and the Commissars," Typescript. (Folder 14)
  - "A Ready-Made Reputation," Typescript., n.d. (Folder 15)
  - "The Red Nightmare," speech, Chicago, Typescript with annotations., n.d. (Folder 16)
  - "The Red Sell," Typescript., n.d. (Folder 17)
  - Response to critical article by Moishe Nadir, Typescript. Included is a clipping in Hebrew., n.d. (Folder 18)
  - "Scoreboard of Soviet Promises," Typescript., n.d. (Folder 19)
  - "Soviet Russia: Its Regime and Its People," Typescript. (Folder 20)
  - Stalin interview, notes on, Typescript., n.d. (Folder 21)
  - "A Strategy Against Communism," Typescript., n.d. (Folder 22)
  - "The Vlasov Movement," Parts I-III, North American Alliance, Typescript., n.d. (Folder 23)
  - "Second Generation Aliens," The Nation, Printed copy., April 25, 1923. (Folder 24)
  - "A Code of Conduct for Soviet Youth," Literary Digest, Printed copy., February 17, 1934. (Folder 25)
  - "Farewell to Moscow," New Outlook, Printed copy., March 1934. (Folder 26)
  - "Moscow Romance," Typescript., June 23, 1934. (Folder 27)
  - Assignment in Utopia, 1937. Correspondence relating to, 1937-38 (Folder 28-29)
  - Letter to the Editor, Freethinker, Typescript., March 18, 1938. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - "The Menace of Totalitarianism," an address before The Catholic League, New York, Printed copy., April 21, 1940. (Folder 2)
  - The Red Decade, Correspondence relating to, 1941. (Folder 3)
  - "An Open Letter to Vice President Wallace," American Mercury, Printed copy., January 1943. (Folder 4)
  - "Cooperating With Russia," American Mercury, Printed copy., May 1943. (Folder 5)
  - "The Progress of Stalin Worship," American Mercury, Printed copy., June 1943. (Folder 6)
  - "A Letter to American Liberals," American Mercury, Printed copy., May 1944. (Folder 7)
  - If This Be Treason: An Autogiography by Victor Kravchenko (As Told to Eugene Lyons), Typescript., 1946. (Folder 8-11)
  - "Youth Wants to Know," radio broadcast, NBC, Printed copy., March 7, 1954. (Folder 12)
  - "Grandparents," Typescript., April 1954. (Folder 13)
  - "A Call to Anger," American Mercury, Printed copy., December 1954. (Folder 14)
  - "Can We Outlaw War?" radio broadcast discussion, "The American Forum," NBC, Printed copy., May 8, 1955. (Folder 15)
  - "They Chose Freedom, But What Are They Getting?" American Friends of Russian Freedom Bulletin, Printed copy., June 1955. (Folder 16)
  - "Stalin's Ghost As Scapegoat," Human Events, Printed copy., May 12, 1956. (Folder 17)
  - Letter to the Editor, New York Times, Printed copy., June 12, 1957. (Folder 18)
  - "Herbert Hoover: Triumph of Integrity," Human Events, Printed copy., August 3, 1957. (Folder 19)
  - "Khrushchev - The Killer in the Kremlin," The Reader's Digest, Printed copy., September 1957. (Folder 20)
  - "Yugoslav Youth in Revolt," Spokane Review, Printed copy., November 20, 1957. (Folder 21)
  - "Negotiating With the Kremlin," The Reader's Digest, Printed copy., April 1958. (Folder 22)
  - "The Refugee Residue: A Free World Failure," The Reader's Digest, Printed copy., May 1958. (Folder 23)
  - "Soviet Russia: Its Regime and Its People," (?). Typescript with annotations., 1959 (Folder 24)
  - Confidential memorandum on the work of Dr. Max Jaccobson, Typescript., January 19, 1959. (Folder 25)
  - "Why the United States Should Stand Fast in Berlin, Quemoy, and the Middle East," an address before the Detroit Economic Club, Typescript., February 16, 1959. (Folder 26)
  - "Folklore of the Right," National Review, Printed copy., April 11, 1959. (Folder 27)
  - "The Crimes of Khrushchev," Part I, testimony before the House of Representatives, Committee on Un-American Activities, Printed copy., September 4, 1959. (Folder 28)
  - "Coming: A Red Renaissance in America," American Legion Magazine, Typescript., October 1959. (Folder 29)
  - Letter to the Editor, Winston-Salem Journal, Printed copy., October 30, 1959. (Folder 30)
  - Remarks at "Know Your America Week," New Bedford, Massachusetts, Typescript., November 28, 1959. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - "How the Communists Train Cold Warriors," (?). Typewritten draft., 1960 (Folder 2)
  - "Russia's Megaton Poem," Midstream, Autumn Printed copy., 1961. (Folder 3)
  - Remarks on a trip to the Far East and Middle East, Typescript., May 9, 1961. (Folder 4)
  - "Specter of Freedom Over the Kremlin," Typewritten draft with annotations., September 1963. (Folder 5)
  - Herbert Hoover: A Biography, 1964.
    - Correspondence relating to, 1964-65 (Folder 6)
    - Source materials (Folder 7-9)
  - "Russian Labor Camps-1965," Typescript., May 1965. (Folder 10)
  - "Is a New Revolution Brewing in the U.S.S.R.?" The Reader's Digest, Printed copy., October 1965. (Folder 11)
  - David Sarnoff: A Biography, 1966.
    - Correspondence relating to, 1964-66 (Folder 12)
    - Preliminary drafts (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Reviews (Folder 2)
    - Typescript (Folder 3-5)
  - Fifty Years of Soviet Communism, Typescript., 1967. (Folder 6)
  - Operation Suicide, Printed copy., 1967. (Folder 7)
  - Workers' Paradise Lost, 1967
    - Correspondence, readers' reactions
      - 1967 (Folder 8)
      - 1967-69 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Publicity material (Folder 2)
    - Reader's Digest condensation. Printed copy. (Folder 3)
    - Reviews (Folder 4-7)
    - Reviews (Box 11, Folder 1-4)
    - Source materials (Folder 5-6)
  - Speech, University of New Mexico, Typescript., November 7, 1967. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Eulogy for Ida Kohlberg, Typewritten draft., February 13, 1968. (Folder 2)
  - Review of Special Counsel by William Rusher, National Review, Printed copy., June 18, 1968. (Folder 3)
  - Interview with Herbert Hoover Oral History Program, Typescript., October 4, 1968. (Folder 4)
  - Radio interview with Dean Manion, Printed transcript., March 21 and 28, 1971. (Folder 5)
  - Response to News Digest International (Australia), Typewritten letter to the editors., June 1973. (Folder 6)
  - Statement of Principles, Committee to Unite America - For America, Typescript., September 1973. (Folder 7)
  - "Detente: A Western Fantasy," Annotated draft typescript copy., 1974. (Folder 8)
  - Untitled article on Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn, North American Newspaper Alliance, Typescript., January 3, 1974. (Folder 9)
  - "The Gulag Archipelago - Solzhenitsyn May Help West Break Through the Amnesia," North American Newspaper Alliance, Typescript., January 5, 1974. (Folder 10)
  - Remarks at a testimonial for David Martin, Washington Hilton Hotel, Typescript. Newspaper Alliance, Typescript., February 6, 1974. February 15, 1974. (Folder 11)
  - Untitled article on Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn, North American (Folder 11A)
  - "Solzhenitsyn Defused," North American Newspaper Alliance, Typescript., February 16, 1974. (Folder 12)
  - "Panama Canal," North American Newspaper Alliance, Typescript., March 7, 1974. (Folder 13)
  - "Trade With Russia: U.S. Still Hasn't Learned," North American Newspaper Alliance, Typescript., March 7, 1974. (Folder 14)
  - "Panama Canal," North American Newspaper Alliance, Typescript., March 12, 1974. (Folder 15)
  - "'Instant' China Experts: Wrong From the Beginning," North American Newspaper Alliance, Typescript., April 16, 1974. (Folder 16)
  - "The War's Unmentionable Footnote: Solzhenitsyn Reminds World of Tragic Vlasov Episode," North American Newspaper Alliance, Typescript., April 20-21, 1974. (Folder 17)
  - "Hoover: Achievements Have Withstood the Test of Time," North American Newspaper Alliance, Typescript., August 3/4, 1974. (Folder 18)
  - Remarks on Herbert Hoover Centennial, Typewritten draft., August 10, 1974. (Folder 19)
  - Untitled article on the American Revolution, North American Newspaper Alliance, Typescript., February 14, 1975. (Folder 20)
  - "Modern 'George Washington' Bear," North American Newspaper Alliance, Typescript., February 18, 1975. (Folder 21)
  - "The South Vietnamese Vote With Their Feet," North American Newspaper Alliance, Typescript., March 21, 1975. (Folder 22)
  - Allilueva, Svetlana (Folder 23)
  - American-Chilean Council, 1979 (Folder 24)
  - Blacklisting and McCarthyism (Folder 25)
  - Captive Nations
    - 1959-1971 (Folder 26)
    - 1963-65 (Folder 27)
  - China
    - General, 1970-76 (Box 13, Folder 1-4)
    - Foreign relations, 1971-74
  - Cold War, 1960-62 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Communism
    - Cuba (Folder 2)
    - Poland (Folder 3)
    - Vietnam (Folder 4)
  - Farkas, Zoltan, Farkas, Richard, Jeff-Craig Associates, 1975-76 (Folder 5)
  - Lazo, Mario (Folder 6)
  - "Liberal Papers,", 1959-1960 (Folder 7)
  - Mano, Keith (Folder 8)
  - Moore, Fred H. (Folder 9)
  - Overseas Press Club of America, membership directories, 1956-57, 1966, 1980 (Folder 10)
  - Perwicz, Daniel (Folder 11)
  - Rosenberg, Ethel and Julius (Folder 12)
  - Sacco-Vanzetti Case (Folder 13)
  - Seversky, Alexander P. de (Folder 14)
  - Solzhenitsyn, Aleksandr (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Sonnenfeldt, Helmut (Folder 2)
  - Soviet Union
    - General, 1964-1974 (Folder 3)
    - Anti-Semitism (Folder 4)
    - Dissent (Folder 5)
    - Famine, 1932-34 (Folder 6)
    - Forced labor camps (Folder 7)
    - Jewish emigration (Folder 8)
    - Politics and government, 1967-69 (Folder 9)
    - Psychiatry abuse for political repression, 1972-74 (Folder 10)
    - Religion, 1971 (Folder 11)
  - U.S. foreign relations with communist countries, 1959-1973 (Folder 12)
  - U.S. - Soviet relations
    - General
      - 1955-1964 (Folder 13)
      - 1959-1973 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Exchange of technology and trade, 1966-1963 (Folder 2)
    - Trade, 1967-1974 (Folder 3)
  - Witkin, Zara (Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous
    - General (Folder 5)
    - Kataev, Valentin, Squaring the Circle, Includes correspondence, 1931. 1935-37 (Folder 6-7)
    - Navrozov, Lev, "The Invisible War,", 1975 (Folder 8)
    - Zoffer, Gerald, "It's Everybody's Business,", n.d. (Folder 9)
- PAMPHLET FILE, 1929-1976
  - General
    - America's Future, Inc.
      - "Communism - A Plan for World Conquest,", 1976 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - "Readings for Liberty,", 1976 (Folder 11)
    - American-Asian Educational Exchange, "Mao - War or Peace,", 1970 (Folder 12)
    - Bales, James D., "Senator Fulbright's Secret Memorandum,", 1962 (Folder 13)
    - "Bob Considine,", 1975 (Folder 14)
    - Flynn, John T., "While You Slept - Our Tragedy in Asia and Who Made It," Devin-Adair Company, New York, 1958 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - National Strategy Information Center
      - "Problems of Strategy in the Pacific and Indian Oceans,", 1970 (Folder 2)
      - Soviet Policy Warfare Techniques, 1972 (Folder 3)
    - Reader's Digest, The Eisenhower Essays, 1969 (Folder 4)
    - Redemption! Jewish Freedom Letters From Russia, American Jewish Conference on Soviet Jewry, 1972 (Folder 5)
    - Truth About Cuba Committee, "Cuba Disproves the Myth That Poverty is the Cause of Communism,", January 1963 (Folder 6)
    - Young, Patricia, The Death Peddlers: Communist China's Opium War on the West, 1969 (Folder 7)
  - Communist Party of the United States (CPUSA)
    - The Communist Position on the Negro Question, n.d. (Folder 8)
    - Foster, William Z., Questions and Answers on the Piatakov-Radek Trial, Workers Library Publishers, New York, 1937 (Folder 9)
    - Olgin, M. J., Trotskyism: Counter-Revolution in Disguise, World Library Publishers, New York, 1935 (Folder 10)
    - Piatnitsky, O., The World Economic Crisis, World Library Publishers, New York, n.d. (Folder 11)
    - Stalin, Joseph
      - Foundations of Leninism, International Publishers, New York, 1932 (Folder 12)
      - Mastering Bolshevism, Workers Library Publishers, New York, 1937 (Folder 13)
      - The Stakhanov Movement in the Soviet Union, Workers Library Publishers, New York, 1935 (Folder 14)